Hello. My name is Austin Bingham. Welcome to the tenth module of the Python Fundamentals course.
Here we'll cover some topics related to producing working maintainable code in Python.
We'll look at the unittest module, which you can use to automate testing of your code, and we'll look at
the debugger that comes with the Standard Library. After that, we'll briefly cover the basics of packaging
and distributing your code, as well as how to install third party packages.
When we build programs and even minor complexity, there are countless ways for defects to creep into our code.
This can happen when we initially write the code, but we're just as likely to introduce defects when we're
making modifications to it. To help get a handle on defects and keep our code quality high, it's often very
useful to have a set of tests that you can run which will tell you if your code is acting as you expect it to.
To help with this, the Python Standard Library includes the unittest module.
Despite its name, this module provides a flexible framework for automating tests of all sorts from acceptance
tests to integration tests to unit tests. Its key feature, like many testing frameworks in many languages,
is that it makes automated and repeatable tests meaning that you can cheaply and easily verify your code
at any time. The unittest module is built around a handful of key concepts.
At the center of these concepts is a notion of a TestCase, which groups together a set of related individual
test functions. A TestCase is the basic unit of text organization in the unittest framework.
The next important concept is that of fixtures. Fixtures are pieces of code which run before and/or after
every test method. Fixtures are used to make sure that the test environment is in an expected state before
a text is run, for example to create a necessary database table or populate a cache.
Fixtures are then used to clean up any resources that may have been used in a test method.
The final key concept is that of assertions. Assertions are how you can tell the unittest framework to
make specific checks, which determine whether a test passes or fails.
Among other things, assertions can make simple Boolean checks, perform object equality tests, or verify
that the proper exceptions are thrown. If an assertion fails, then a test function fails, so assertions
are really the lowest level of testing you can perform. With those concepts in mind, let's see how to actually
use the unittest module.
For this we'll use Test-Driven Development to write a simple text analysis function.
This function will take in a filename, read the file, and calculate both the number of lines in the file
and the number of characters in the file.
Since this will be an iterative development process, we'll put the code in the file text_analyzer.py
rather than work at the REPL. So to start, let's create our first test with enough supporting code to actually
run it. First we import the unittest module. Next we create our test case by creating a class, TextAnalysisTests,
which derives from unittest.TestCase. This is how you create test cases with the unittest framework.
To define individual test methods in a test case, you simply create methods that start with test_.
These are automatically discovered by the unittest framework and don't require any sort of explicit
registration. In this case, we define the simplest possible test.
Does the analyze text function run at all? This function doesn't make any explicit checks, but rather
it relies on the fact that a test method will fail if it throws any exceptions.
So in this case, if analyze_text() isn't defined, then this test will fail.
Finally, we define the idiomatic main block, which calls unittest.main() when this module is executed.
Unittest.main() will search for all test case subclasses in a module and execute all of their test methods.
Since we're using test
driven design here, we expect our tests to fail at first, and indeed this fails spectacularly for the simple
reason that we haven't defined the necessary function yet. Unittest.main() produces a simple report
telling us how many tests were run and how many failed. It also shows us how the tests failed, in this case
showing us that we got a NameError when we tried to run the nonexistent function analyze_text().
Let's fix that by adding the function. Remember that in Test-Driven Development we only write enough
code to satisfy our tests, so all we do now is create an empty function.
Running the test again, we find that we now pass.
The next thing we want to do is to be able to pass a filename to analyze_text() so that it knows what to process.
For this to make sense, we want the filename to represent an actual file.
To make sure that a file exists, we're going to define some fixtures.
The first fixture we can define is a method on the test case called setUp.
This function is run before each test method. In this case, we'll use setUp to create a file for us and remember
the filename as a member of the test case. The second fixture available to us is another test case method
called tearDown. TearDown is run after each test method, and in this case we're going to use it to delete
the file we created in setUp. And since we're using the OS module and tearDown, we need to import it at the
top of the file. Notice how tearDown swallows any exceptions thrown by os.remove.
We do this because tearDown can't actually be certain that the file exits, so it simply tries to remove
the file, and it assumes that any failure is acceptable. With our two fixtures in place, we now have a file
that is created before each test method, and we just delete it after each test method.
This means that each test method is starting in a stable, known state.
This is critical to making reproducible tests. You may have noticed that the setUp and tearDown function
names aren't inline with what PEP-8 prescribes. This is because the unittest module predates those parts
of PEP-8, which specify the convention of function names being in lowercase with underscores.
There are several such cases in the Python Standard Library, but most new Python code follows the PEP-8 style.
Now that we have a filename that we can pass to analyze_text(), let's pass it in by modifying our existing test.
Since the self argument passed to the fixture is the same instance as that passed to the test methods, our
tests can access the filename attribute created in setUp.
Of course this test fails because analyze_text() doesn't accept any arguments yet.
That's simple enough to fix.
And now we're passing again.
Now that we're satisfied that the function exists and accepts the right number of arguments, let's see
if we can make it do real work. The first thing we want is for the function to return the number of lines in
the file, so let's define that test. Here we see our first example of an assertion.
The TestCase class has many assertion methods, and in this case we used assertEqual to check that the number
of lines counted by our function is equal to 4. If the value returned by analyze_text is not equal to 4, this
assertion will cause the test method to fail,
and that is precisely what happens. We can now see that we're running two tests, that one of them passes
and that the new fails with an AssertionError.
Let's break from the TDD rules and move a bit faster now. First we'll update the function to return the number
of lines in the file, (Typing)
and this gives good results.
So, let's add a test for the other feature we want, which is to count the number of characters in the file.
Since the function is now supposed to return two values, we'll have it return a tuple with a line count in
the first position and character count in the second. Our new test looks like this,
and it fails as expected. This tells us that it can't index into the integer returned by analyze_text,
so let's fix analyze_text to return the proper tuple.
This fixes our new test, but we find we've broken an old one.
But that's easy enough to fix because all we need to do is account for the new return type, and now
everything is passing again.
Another thing we want to test for is that analyze_text throws the correct exception when it is passed a
non-existent filename. Here we see the use of the assertRaises assertion.
This assertion checks that the specified exception type, in this case IOError, is thrown from the body
of the with block.
Since open raises IOError for non-existent files, our test already passes.
Finally, we can see one more very useful type of assertion if we write a test to verify that analyze_text
doesn't delete the file, a reasonable requirement for the function.
AssertTrue simply checks that the value passed into it evaluates to true.
There is an equivaluent assertFalse, which does the same thing, but for false values.
As you might imagine, this test passes already as well. So, now
now we've got a useful, passing set of tests. This example is small, but it demonstrates many of the important
parts of the unittest module. There are many more parts of unittest, but you can get quite far using just
the techniques we've seen here.