In this last section, we'll take a look at how to install third-party Python code into your installation.
There are a number of ways to do this, and we'll cover three of the most common:
Distutils, easy_install, and pip. We won't cover them in great detail, but we'll look at basic usage,
and you'll learn enough to use them for straightforward installation purposes.
The first option, distutils, we saw in the previous section when we created a setup.py and used the install
option. Almost all Python projects include a setup.py, so knowing how to use it is invaluable if some of
the other more convenient methods fail. Since we covered distutils in the previous section, there's
no real need to go over it here. Just remember the basic python setup.py install command.
The other two tools we'll look at are easy_install and pip. Both of these tools do essentially the same thing.
They search for packages in a central repository, the Python package index or PyPI, also known by the nickname
cheeseshop, and then download and install them along with their dependencies.
You can browse the cheeseshop at pypi.python.org/pypi. This is an extremely convenient way to install
Python software, so it's good to understand how to use it. To use these tools, we need to first make sure
they're installed. Fortunately, if you can install easy_install, you can use it to install pip, so we'll
install easy_install first.
Start a new command prompt, and go to the palindrome directory that you created earlier.
You should have a virtual environment there in the venv directory, so let's activate that now.
Once you've activated the environment, you need to download distribute_setup.py into your palindrome
directory. This script can be used to install the easy_install tools, so let's do that now.
Once you have easy_install installed, you can use it to install other third-party software.
The basic syntax for installing via easy_install is easy_install followed by the package's name.
So, for example, to install the eagertools package, you can simply run easy_install eagertools.
As you can see, this goes to the Python package index, downloads a tarball, runs its setup.py to create
a binary distribution, and then copies that distribution into your virtual environment's site-packages
directory. If you now run Python, you'll see that you can import eagertools.
Now that we've got easy_install working, we can use it to install pip.
Just as we did with the eagertools, we just run a simple command.
In this case, the installation is a bit more involved. In particular, we see that easy_install not only
installed a module in the site-packages, but it also installed the pip executable into the bin directory.
With pip installed, you should be pretty comfortable with how to use easy_install.
So, now we'll switch to using pip to do one final installation.
For this example, we'll install the nose testing tool. Nose is a sort of power tool for running unittest-
based tests such as those we've been developing in this module.
One really useful thing it can do is discover all of your tests and run them.
This means that you don't need to add unittest. main into your code.
You could just use nose to find and run your tests. So, let's use pip to install nose.
Pip uses subcommands to decide what to do, and to install modules you use pip install &lt;package name&gt;.
We see quite a bit happening here, much of it having to do with making sure that nose is ready to run on our
Python installation. In the end though, it installs the nose module as we can see.
More interestingly, it installs the nosetests program in the bin directory.
To really put the icing on the cake, let's use nosetests to run the tests in palindrome.py.