First, what's so great about Python? Why do you want to learn it?
There are lots of good answers to those questions. One is
that Python is powerful. The Python language is expressive and productive.
It comes with a great standard library, and it's the center of a huge universe of wonderful third-party
libraries. With Python you can build everything from simple scripts to complex applications, you can
do it quickly, you can do it safely, and you can do it with fewer lines of code than you might think possible.
But that's just part of what makes Python great.
Another is that Python is wonderfully open. It's open source, so you can get to know every aspect of it if
you want. At the same time, Python is hugely popular and has a great community to support you when you run
into problems. This combination of openness and large user base means that almost anyone from casual
programmers to professional software developers can engage with the language at the level they need.
Another benefit of a large user base is that Python is showing up in more and more places.
You may be wanting to learn Python simply because it's the language of some technology you want to use,
and this is not surprising. Many of the most popular web and scientific packages in the world are written
in Python. But for many people these reasons take backseat to something more important.
Python is fun. Python's expressive readable style, quick edit and run development cycle, and batteries
included philosophy mean that you can sit down and enjoy writing code rather than fighting compilers
and thorny syntax. And Python will grow with you. As your experiments become prototypes and your prototypes
become products, Python makes the experience of writing software not just easier, but truly enjoyable.
In the words of Randall Munroe, "Come join us. Programming is fun again."