Let's look at how all of this relates to function arguments and return values.
Let's define a function at the REPL, which appends a value to a list and prints the modified list.
First the list and then a function modify, which appends to and prints the list.
The function accepts a single formal argument named K. We call modify passing our list M as a the actual
argument, which indeed prints the modified list with four elements.
But what does our list reference outside the function now refer to?
The list referred to by M has been modified because it is the self-same list referred to by K inside the function.
When we pass an object reference to a function, we're essentially assigning from the actual argument
reference, in this case M, to the formal argument reference, in this case K.
As we have seen, assignment causes the reference being assigned to refer to the same object as the reference
being assigned from. This is exactly what's going on here. If you want a function to modify a copy of an object,
it's the responsibility of the function to do the copying.
Let's look at another example, first a new list F that refers the three elements, then a function which
replaces the list, which we now call with the actual argument F.
This is much as we'd expect; however, what's the value of F? F still refers to the original unmodified list.
This time the function did not modify the object that was passed in.
What's going on?
Well, the object reference named F was assigned to the formal argument named G, so G and F did indeed refer
to the same object just as in the previous example. However, on the first line of the function we reassigned
the reference G to point it to a newly constructed list 17, 28, 45, so within the function the reference
to the original 14, 23, 37 list was overwritten, although the unmodified object itself was still pointed
to by the F reference outside the function. So, we see that it's quite possible to modify the objects through
function argument references, but also possible to rebind the argument reference to new values.
If you wanted to change the contents of the list and have the changes seen outside the function, you could
modify the contents of the list like this, (Typing) and indeed the contents of F have been modified.
Function arguments are transferred by what is called pass by object reference.
This means that the value of the reference is copied into the function argument, not the value of the referred
object. No objects are copied.
The return statement uses the same pass by object reference semantics as function arguments.
We can demonstrate this simply by writing a simple function which returns its only argument.
Creating an object such as a list and passing it through this simple function returns the very same object
we passed in showing that no copies of the list were made.