As we have seen, no type declarations are necessary, and variables are essentially just untyped name
bindings to objects. As such, they can be rebound or reassigned as often as necessary, even to objects
of different types. But when we bind a name to an object, where is that binding stored?
To answer that question, we must look at scopes and scoping rules in Python.
There are four main types of scope in Python arranged in a hierarchy.
Each scope is a context in which names are stored in which they can be looked up.
The four scopes from narrowest to broadest are: Local, those names defined inside the current function.
Enclosing, those names defined inside any and all enclosing functions.
This scope isn't important for the contents of this Python fundamentals course.
Global, those names defined at the top level of a module. Each module brings with it a new global scope.
And finally Built-in, those names built into the Python language through the special built-ins module.
Together these scopes comprise the LEGB rule. Names are looked up in the narrowest relevant context.
It's important to note that scopes in Python do not correspond to the source code blocks as demarcated
by indentation. For-loops, with-blocks, and the like do not introduce new nested scopes.
Consider our words.py module. It contains the following global names:
Main bound by the def main statement, sys bound when sys is imported, __name__ provided by the Python runtime,
urlopen bound from the urllib request module, fetch_words bound by the def fetch_words statement, and
print_items bound by the def print_items statement. Module scope name bindings are typically introduced
by import statements and function or class definitions. It is possible to use other objects at module
scope, and this is typically used for constants, although it can be used for variables.
Within the fetch_words function we have the six local names: Word bound by the inner for-loop, line_words
bound by assignment, line bound by the outer for-loop, story_words bound by assignment, url bound by
the formal function argument, and story bound by the with statement.
Each of these is brought into existence at first use and continues to live within the function scope until
the function completes at which point the references will be destroyed.
Very occasionally we need to rebind a global name at module scope from within a function.
Consider the following simple module.
If we save this module in scopes.py, we can import it into the REPL for experimentation.
When show_count() is called, Python looks up the count name in the local namespace L, doesn't find it,
so it looks in the next most outer namespace, in this case the global module namespace G where it finds the
name count and prints the referred object.
Now we call set_count with a new value and call show_count again.
You might be surprised that show_count displays 0 after the call to set_count, so let's work through what's
happening.
When we call set_count, the assignment count = c binds the object referred to by the formal argument C to
a new name count in the innermost namespace context, which is the scope of the current function.
No lookup is performed for the global count at module scope. We have created a new variable which shadows
and thereby prevents access to the global of the same name. To avoid this situation, we need to instruct
Python to consider use of the count name in the set_count function to resolve to the count in the module namespace.
We can do this by using the global keyword. Let's modify set_count to do so.
Quit and restart the Python interpreter and exercise our revised module, which now demonstrates the
required behavior.