In Python it's important to remember that everything is an object, primitive objects, functions, modules,
and on and on. It's easy to see that when you start to explore even simple pieces of code.
Let's go back to our words module and experiment with it further at the REPL.
On this occasion we'll import just the module. The import statement binds a module object to the name words
in the current namespace. We can determine the type of any object by using the type built-in function.
If we want to see the attributes of an object, we can use the dir built-in function in a Python interactive
session to introspect an object. The dir function returns a sorted list of the module attributes including
the ones we defined such as the function fetch words, any imported names such as sys and urlopen, and various
special attributes delimited by double underscores such as double underscore name and double underscore
doc, which reveal the inner workings of Python. We can use the type function on any of these attributes
to learn more about them. For instance, we can see that fetch_words is a function object.
We can in turn call dir on the function to reveal its attributes, and we see that function objects have many
special attributes to do with how Python functions are implemented behind the scenes.
For now, we'll just look at a couple of simple attributes. As you might expect, this is the name of the function
object as a string, and this is the docstring we provided. These give us some clues as to how the built-in
help function might be implemented.