Let's sum up. First, we looked at strings, in particular the various forms of quoting for single- and multi-
line strings. We saw how adjacent string literals are implicitly concatenated.
Python has support for universal newlines, so no matter what platform you're using, it's sufficient
to use a single slash N character safe in the knowledge that it will be appropriately translated to and
from the native newline during I/O. Escape sequences provide an alternative means of incorporating
newlines and other control characters into literal strings. The backslashes used for escaping can be
a hindrance for Windows file system paths or regular expressions, so raw strings with an R prefix can be
used to suppress the escaping mechanism. Other types such as integers can be converted to strings using
the str() constructor. Individual characters returned as one character strings can be retrieved using
square brackets with integer zero-based indices. Strings support a rich variety of operations such
as splitting through their methods. In Python 3 literal strings can contain Unicode characters directly
in the source. The bytes type has many of the capabilities of strings, but is a sequence of bytes rather
than a sequence of Unicode codepoints. Bytes literals are prefixed with a lowercase B.
To covert between string and bytes instances, we use the encode() method of str and the decode() method
of bytes in both cases passing the encoding, which we must know in advance.
Lists are mutable, heterogeneous sequences of objects. List literals are delimited by square brackets,
and the items are separated by commas. As with strings, individual elements can be retrieved by indexing
into a list with square brackets. In contrast to strings, individual list elements can be replaced by
assigning to the indexed item. Lists can be grown by appending to them and can be constructed from other
sequences using the list() constructor.
Dictionaries associate keys with values. Literal dictionaries are delimited by curly braces.
The key value pairs are separated from each other by commas, and each key is associated with its corresponding
value with a colon.
For-loops take items one-by-one from an iterable object such as a list and bind the name to the current item.
For-loops correspond to what are called for-each loops in other languages.
Thanks for watching, and we'll see you in the next module.