Dictionaries are completely fundamental to the way the Python language works and are very widely used.
A dictionary maps keys to values and in some languages is known as an associate of array.
Let's look at how to create and use them in Python.
Literal dictionaries are created using curly braces containing key value pairs.
Each pair is separated by a comma, and each key is separated from the corresponding value by a colon.
Here we use a dictionary to create a simple telephone directory.
We can retrieve items by key using the square brackets operator and update the values associated with
the key by assigning through the square brackets. If we assign to a key that has not yet been added, a new
entry is created. Be aware that the entries in the dictionary can't be relied upon to be stored in any particular
order. Similarly to lists, empty dictionaries can be created using empty curly braces.
We'll revisit dictionaries in much more detail in Module 5.