In this last section before we summarize, we're going to write a longer snippet at the REPL and briefly
introduce the with-statement. We're going to fetch some text data for some classic literature from the
web using a Python Standard Library function called the urlopen.
To get access to urlopen, we need to import the function
from the request module within the standard library urllib package.
Next we're going to call urlopen with a URL to our story. We'll be using a Python construct called a with
block to manage the resource returned by the URL since under the hood fetching the resource from the web
requires operating system sockets and such like. We'll be talking more about with-statements in a later module,
but for now it's enough to know that using a with-statement with objects which use external resources
such as this is very good practice to avoid resource leaks.
The with-statement calls the urlopen function and binds the response to a variable named story.
Notice that the with-statement is terminated by a colon introducing a new block, so we indent four spaces
and create an empty list, which ultimately will
hold all of the words from the text.
Next we open a for-loop, which will work through the story. Recall that for-loops request items one-by-
one from the term on the right of the in keyword, in this case story, and assign them in turn to the name on
the left, in this case line. It so happens that the type of HTTP response represented by story yields successive
lines of text when iterated over in this way.
So, the for-loop retrieves one line of text at a time from Dickens' classic.
Note also that the for-statement is terminated by a colon because it introduces the body of the for-loop,
which is a new block and hence a further level of indentation.
For each line of text we use the split method to divide it into words on whitespace boundaries
resulting in a list of words we call line words.
Now we use a second for-loop nested inside the first to iterate over this list of words appending each in
turn to the accumulating story_words list. Finally, we enter a blank line at the three dots prompt to close
all open blocks. In this case, the inner for-loop, the outer for-loop, and the with-block will all be terminated.
The block will be executed, and after a short delay Python now returns us to the regular triple arrow prompt.
At this point, if Python gives you an error such as a syntax error or indentation error, you should go back,
review what you have entered, and carefully reenter the code until Python accepts the whole block without
complaint. If you get an HTTP error, then you were unable to fetch the resource over the internet, and you
should try again later, although it's worth checking that you have typed the URL correctly.
We can now look at those words simply by asking Python to evaluate the value of story_words.
Here we can see the list of words. Notice that each of the single quoted words is prefixed by a lowercase B
meaning that we have a list of bytes objects where we would have preferred a list of strings.
This is because the HTTP request transferred raw bytes to us over the network.
To get a list of strings, we should decode the byte stream in each line into UTF-8 Unicode strings.
We can do this by inserting a call to the decode method of the bytes object and then operating on the resulting
Unicode string. The Python REPL supports a simple command line history, and by careful use of the up and
down arrows we can reenter our snippet. When we get to the line which needs to be changed, we can edit it using
the left and right arrow keys to insert the requisite call to decode.
Then when we rerun the block and take a fresh look at story_words we should see we have a list of strings.
We've just about reached the limit of what's possible to comfortably edit at the Python REPL, so in the
next course module we'll look at how to move this code into a Python module where it can be more easily worked
within a text editor.