Now we'll look at how our generator functions, which resume execution each time the next value is requested,
can maintain state in local variables. In the process of doing so, our generators will be both more interesting
and useful. The resumable nature of generator functions can result in complex control flow, so we'll
be watching the execution of these generators in a graphical Python debugger.
I'll be using PyCharm, but you can use any Python debugger to trace generator execution.
We'll be showing two generators which demonstrate lazy evaluation, which will then combine into a generator
pipeline.
The first generator we'll look at is called take, which retrieves a specified number of elements from
the front of a sequence. Note that the function defines a generator because it contains at least one yield
statement. This particular generator also contains a return statement to terminate the stream of yielded
values. The generator simply uses a counter to keep track of how many elements have been yielded so far
ending the sequence when we reach a specified count. Since generators are lazy and only produce values
on request, we'll drive execution with a for loop and a run_take function.
In run_take we create a source list called items, which we pass to our generator function along with a count
of 3. Internally the for loop will use the iterator protocol to retrieve values from the take generator
until it terminates. Once execution begins, the for loop in run_take requests a value from take, which
runs until it encounters the yield statement. At this point control returns to run_take, which prints
the value until we get to the next iteration of what is in effect the outer for loop.
Each iteration of the outer loop causes execution to be transferred back into run_take just sufficiently
to yield the next value. Eventually the counter variable is equal to the counter argument and will literally
return from run_take. Behind the scenes this raises a StopIteration exception, which is caught by the
internal machinery of the for loop in run_take. This is the signal that take has done its work, so the for
loop exits, and the program completes. Now let's bring our second generator into the picture.
This generator function called distinct eliminates duplicate items by keeping track of which elements
it's already seen in a set. In this generator we also make use of a control flow construct we have not previously
seen, the continue keyword. The continue statement finishes the current iteration of the loop and begins
the next iteration immediately. When executed in this case, execution will be transferred back to the
for statement, but as with break it can also be used with while loops.
In this case, the continue is used to skip any values which have already been yielded.
As execution starts, the for loop and run_distinct() request a value from distinct.
This runs until it reaches yield, which on this iteration simply returns the first item retrieved by this
inner for loop form the items list. Control flow transfers to run_distinct, which prints the value and
proceeds with its next iteration. Note how when execution of distinct resumes we actually complete the
work of the previous iteration by remembering the value just yielded before getting on with the most recently
requested value. We can do this because item is not reassigned until we get back to the for statement.
On the third iteration, the next item retrieved from the source is already present in the seen set.
Control enters the if block, and the continue statement is executed transferring control back to the
beginning of the innermost loop. Eventually the items list is exhausted.
The generator returns implicitly at the end, the for loop and run_distinct completes, and the program exits.
Now we'll arrange both of our generators into a lazy pipeline using take and distinct together to fetch
the first three unique items from a collection. A coherent verbal description of step-by-step execution
of a generator pipeline may not even be possible, but that's not going to stop us trying.
When execution starts, distinct must be called first in order to produce the argument for take.
Of course distinct returns the generator object over which take will be iterating.
In turn, the generator object returned by take will be iterated over by the for loop in our run_pipline
driver function. This part of the process is hidden from the view of the debugger.
When the outermost loop in run_pipeline requests its first value, execution is transferred to take.
Remember, the iterable over which take is looping is the generator produced by distinct.
When the for loop and take request the first value from this generator, control is transferred to distinct.
Distinct now runs until it reaches the yield at which point it is returning the first item from the source
list, 3. The value is yielded back to the for loop intake, which executes until it in turn yields the value
back to the loop in run_pipeline, which only now starts its first iteration printing the first value.
Execution continues in this interleaved manner until the first three distinct values have been yielded
and printed. The advantage of this approach is that distinct only does just enough work to yield the first
three distinct values rather than processing its whole source list.
It pays to be lazy.