Hello. My name is Austin Bingham. Welcome to the sixth module of the Python Fundamentals course where
we introduce exception handling techniques.
Exception handling is a mechanism for stopping normal program flow and continuing at some surrounding
context or code block.
The event of interrupting normal flow is called the act of raising an exception.
In some enclosing context the raise exception must be handled upon which control flow if transferred
to the exception handler. If an exception propagates up the call stack to the start of the program, then
an unhandled exception will cause the program to terminate. And exception object containing information
about where and why an exceptional event occurred is transported from the point at which the exception
was raised to the exception handler so that the handler can interrogate the exception object and take
appropriate action.
If you've used exceptions in other popular imperative languages like C++ or Java, then you've already
got a good idea of how exceptions work in Python.
There have been long and tiresome debates over exactly what constitutes an exceptional event, the core
issue being that exceptionality is in reality a matter of degree, some things are more exceptional than
others, whereas programming languages impose a false dichotomy by insisting that an event is entirely
exceptional or not at all exceptional. The Python philosophy is at the liberal end of the spectrum when
it comes to the use of exceptions. Exceptions are ubiquitous in Python, and it's crucial to understand
how to handle them.