Now let's look at another tenant of Python philosophy and culture, the idea that it's easier to ask forgiveness
than permission. There are only two approaches to dealing with a program operation that might fail.
The first approach is to check that all the preconditions for a failure-prone operation are met in advance
of attempting the operation. The second approach is to blindly hope for the best, but be prepared to deal
with the consequences if it doesn't work out.
In Python culture, these two philosophies are known as Look Before You Leap, LBYL, and It's Easier to Ask
Forgiveness than Permission, EAFP, which incidentally was coined by Rear Admiral Grace Hopper, inventor
of the compiler. Python is strongly in favor of EAFP because it puts primary logic for the happy path in
its most readable form with deviations from the normal flow handled separately rather than interspersed
with the main flow. Let's consider an example, processing a file.
The details of the processing aren't relevant. All we need to know is that the process_file function will
open a file and read some data from it.
First the LBYL version. Before attempting to call process_file, we check that the files exists, and if
it doesn't we avoid making the call and print a helpful message instead.
There are several problems with this approach, some obvious and some insidious.
One obvious problem is that we only perform an existence check.
What if the file exists, but contains garbage? What if the path refers to a directory instead of a file?
According to LBYL, we should add preemptive tests for these too.
A more subtle problem is that there is a race condition here. It's possible for the file to be deleted, for
example by another process, between the existence check and the process_file call, a classic atomicity issue.
There's really no good way to deal with this. Handling of errors from process_file will be needed in any case.
Now consider the alternative using the more Pythonic EAFP approach.
Here we simply attempt the operation without checks in advance, but we have an exception handler in place
to deal with any problems. We don't even need to know in a lot of detail exactly what might go wrong.
Here we catch OSError, which covers all manner of conditions such as file not found and using directories
where files are expected.
EAFP is standard in Python, and that philosophy is enabled by exceptions.
Without exceptions, that is using error codes instead, you are forced to include error handling directly
in the main flow of the logic. Since exceptions interrupt the main flow, they allow you to handle exceptional
cases non-locally.
Exceptions coupled with EAFP are also superior because unlike error codes exceptions cannot be easily ignored.
By default, exceptions have a big effect whereas error codes are silent by default, so the exception EAFP-
base style makes it very difficult for problems to be silently ignored.