Sometimes you need to perform a cleanup action irrespective of whether an operation succeeds.
In a later module we'll introduce context managers, which are the modern solution to this common situation,
but here we'll introduce the try…finally construct since creating a context manager can be overkill
in simple cases. And in any case, an understanding of try…finally is useful for making your own context managers.
Consider this function, which uses various facilities of the Standard Library's OS module to change
the current working directory, create a new directory at that location, and then restore to the original
working directory. At first sight this seems reasonable, but should the call to os.mkdir fail for some
reason, the current working directory of the Python process won't be restored to its original value,
and the make_at function will have had an unintended side effect.
To fix this, we'd like the function to restore the original current working directory under all circumstances.
We can achieve this with a try…finally block. Code in the finally-block is executed whether execution
leaves the try-block normally by reaching the end of the block or exceptionally by an exception being raised.
This construct can be combined with except blocks, here used to add a simple further logging facility.
Now if the os.mkdir call raises an OSError, the OS handler will be run, and the exception will be re-raised.
But since the finally block is always run no matter how the try block ends, we can be sure that the final directory
change will take place in all circumstances.