Detecting a single keypress from Python such as the press any key to continue functionality at the console
requires use of operating system specific modules. We can't use the built-in input function because
that waits for the user to press Return before giving us a string.
To implement this on Windows, we need to use functionality from the Windows only msvcrt module, and on
Linux and Mac OS X we need to use functionality from the Unix only tty and termios modules in addition to
the sys module.
This example is quite instructive as it demonstrates many Python language features including import
and def as statements as opposed to declarations. Recall the top level module code is executed on first import.
Within the first try block we attempt to import msvcrt, the Microsoft Visual C runtime.
If this succeeds, we then proceed to define a function getkey(), which delegates to the msvcrt.getch()
function. Even though we are inside a try block at this point, the function will be declared at the current
scope, which is the module scope. If, however, the import of msvcrt fails because we're not running on
Windows, an ImportError will be raised, and execution will transfer to the except block.
This is a case of an error being silenced explicitly because we're going to attempt an alternative course
of action in the exception handler. Within the except block we import three modules needed for a getkey()
implementation on Unix-like systems, and then proceed to the alternative definition of getkey(), which
again binds the function implementation to a name in the module scope.
This Unix implementation of getkey() uses a try…finally construct to restore various terminal attributes
after the terminal has been put into raw mode for the purposes of reading a single character.
In the event that our program is running on neither Windows nor a Unix-like system, the import tty statement
will raise a second import error. This time we make no attempt to intercept this exception.
We allow it to propagate to our caller, which is whatever attempted to import this keypress module.
We know how to signal this error, but not how to handle it, so we defer that decision to our caller.
The error will not pass silently. If the caller has more knowledge or alternative tactics available,
it can in turn intercept this exception and take appropriate action, perhaps degrading to using Python's
input built-in function and giving a different message to the user.