Since exceptions are a means of control flow, they can be clumsy to demonstrate at the REPL, so for this
part of the course we'll be using a Python module to contain our code.
Let's start with a very simple module we can use for exploring these important concepts and behaviors.
Place this code in a module called exceptional.py.
Import the convert function from this module into the Python REPL and call our function with a string to
see that it has the desired effect. But if we call our function with an object that can't be converted to
an integer, we get a traceback from the int call.
What's happened here is that the int constructor raised an exception because it couldn't sensibly perform
the conversion. We didn't have a handler in place, so it was caught by the REPL and the stack trace was displayed.
The ValueError referred to in the stack trace is the type of the exception object, and the error message
invalid literal for int() with base 10: 'hedgehog' is part of the payload of the exception object that
has been retrieved and printed by the REPL.
Notice the exception propagates across several levels in the call stack.