Let's add a second function string_log to our module, which calls our convert function and computes the
natural log of the result. At this point we must confess that we've gone out of way here to be deeply unpythonic
by wrapping the perfectly good int conversion included with Python, which raises exceptions on failure,
in our convert function, which returns a good old fashioned negative error code.
Rest assured that this unforgivable Python heresy has been committed solely to demonstrate the greatest
folly of error return codes, that they can be ignored by the caller wreaking havoc amongst unsuspecting
code later in the program.
A slightly better program might test the value of V before proceeding to the log call.
Without such a check, log will of course fail when passed the negative error code value.
Naturally, the log failure causes the raising of another exception.
Much better, and altogether more Pythonic, is to forget about error codes completely and go back to rasing
an exception from convert.