Exceptions form an important aspect of the API of a function.
Callers of a function need to know which exceptions to expect under various conditions so that they can
ensure appropriate exception handlers are in place. We'll use a square root finding as an example using
a home-grown square root function courtesy of Heron of Alexandria, although he probably didn't use Python.
Place the following code in a file called roots.py. There's only one language feature in this program
we haven't met before, the logical and operator, which we use in this case to test that two conditions are
true on each iteration of the loop. Python also includes a logical or operator, which can be used to test
whether either or both operands are true.
Running our program, we can see that Heron was really onto something.
Let's add a new line to the main() function, which takes the square root of -1.
If we run that, we get a new exception. What has happened is that Python has intercepted a division by 0,
which occurs on the second iteration of the loop and raises an exception, a ZeroDivisionError.
Let's modify our code to catch the exception before it propagates up to the top of the call stack, thereby
causing our program to stop using the try except construct.
Now when we run the script we see that we're handling the exception cleanly.
We should be careful to avoid a beginner's mistake of having two tight scopes for exception handling blocks.
We can easily use one try except blocks for all of our calls to square root.
We also need a third print statement to show how execution of the enclosed block is terminated.
This is an improvement on what we started with, but most likely users of a square root function don't expect
it to throw a ZeroDivisionError. Python provides us with several standard exception types to signal
common errors. If a function parameter is supplied with an illegal value, it is customary to raise a ValueError.
We can do this by using the raise keyword with a newly created exception object, which we can create by calling
the ValueError constructor.
There are two places we could deal with the division by zero. The first approach would be to wrap the root
finding while loop in a try except ZeroDivisionError construct and then raise a new ValueError exception
from inside the exception handler. This would be wasteful though.
We know this routine will fail with negative numbers, so we can detect this free condition early on and
raise an exception at that point. This is a simple if statement and a call to raise passing the new exception
object. The ValueError constructor accepts an error message.
See how we also modify the docstring to make it plain which exception type will be raised by a square root
and under what circumstances.
But look what happens if we run the program. We're still getting a traceback and an ungraceful program exit.
This happens because we forgot to modify our exception handler to catch ValueError rather than
ZeroDivisionError.
Let's modify our calling code to catch the right exception class and also assign the caught exception
object to a named variable so we can interrogate it after it has been caught.
In this case, our interrogation is simply to print the exception object, which knows how to display itself
as the message to standard error.
Running the program again, we can see that our exception is being handled gracefully.