We tend to not protect against TypeErrors in Python. To do so runs against the grain of dynamic typing in
Python and limits the reuse potential of the code that we write.
For example, we could test whether an argument was an int using the built-in isinstance function and raise
a TypeError exception if it was not, but then we'd also want to allow arguments that are instances of float
as well. It soon gets complicated if we want to check whether our function will work with types such as rational,
complex, or any other kind of number. And in any case, who's to say that it does?
Alternatively, we could intercept TypeError inside our square root function and re-raise it, but to what end?
Usually in Python it's not worth adding type checking to your functions.
If a function works with a particular type, even one you couldn't have known about when you designed your
function, then that's all to the good.
If not, execution will probably result in a TypeError anyway. Likewise, we tend to not catch TypeErrors
very frequently either.