Hello. My name is Robert Smallshire. Welcome to the ninth module of the Python Fundamentals course where
we'll cover reading and writing data from text and binary files and discover how to manage resources such
as files elegantly using context managers.
To open a file in Python, we call the built-in open() function.
This takes a number of arguments, but the most commonly used are:
File, the path to the file. This is required. Mode, which specifies read/write/append, and binary or
text mode. This is optional, but we always recommend specifying it for clarity.
Explicit is better than implicit. Encoding. If the file contains encoded text data, this is the text encoding
to use. It's often a good idea to specify this. If you don't specify it, Python will choose a default encoding
for you, which may not be what you want.
At the file system level, files contain only a series of bytes.
Python distinguishes between files opened in binary and text modes even when the underlying operating
system doesn't.
Files opened in binary mode return and manipulate their contents as bytes objects without any decoding.
Binary mode files reflect the raw data in the file.
A file opened in text mode treats its contents as if it contains text strings of the str type, the raw bytes
having first been decoded using a platform dependent encoding or using the specified encoding if given.
By default, text mode also engages support for Python's universal newlines.
This causes translation between a single portable newline character in our program strings, /n, and
a platform-dependent newline representation in the raw bytes stored in the file system, for example
carriage return newline /r/n on Windows.
Getting the encoding right is crucial for correctly interpreting the contents of a text file, which is
why we label the point. If you don't specify an encoding, Python will use the default from
sys.getdefaultencoding. In our case, that's a UTF-8, but there's no guarantee that the default encoding
on your system is the same as the default encoding on another system with which you wish to exchange files.
Better for all concerned to make a conscious decision about the text bytes encoding.
You can get a list of supported text encodings in the Python documentation.