Dealing with binary files often requires pulling apart or assembling data at the byte level.
This is exactly what our _int32_to_bytes function is doing. We'll take a quick look at it because it shows
some features of Python we haven't seen before. The function uses the bitwise shift and bitwise and operators
to extract individual bytes from the integer value. Notice that bitwise and uses the ampersand symbol
to distinguish it from the logical and, which is the spelled out word.
The double arrow is the right shift operator, which shifts the binary representation of the integer right
by the specified number of bits. The routine shifts the integer 1, 2, and 3 bytes to the right before extracting
the least significant byte with the bitwise and at each position.
The four resulting integers are used to construct a tuple, which is then passed to the bytes constructor
to produce a 4-byte sequence.