We're not going to write a full-blown BMP reader, although that would be an interesting exercise.
We'll just make a simple function to determine the image dimension and pixels from a BMP file.
We'll add the code into bmp.py. Of course we use a with statement to manage the file so we don't have to worry
about it being properly closed. Inside the with-block we perform a simple validation check by looking
at the first two magic bytes that we expect in a bmp file. If they're not present, we raise a ValueError,
which will of course cause the context manager to close the file.
Looking back at our BMP writer we can determine that the image dimensions are stored exactly 18 bytes from
the beginning of the file. We seek to that location and use the read method to read two chunks of 4 bytes each
for the two 32-bit integers, which represent the dimensions. Because we opened the file in binary mode,
read returns a bytes object. We pass each of these two bytes objects to another implementation detail
method _bytes_to_int32, which assembles them back into an integer.
The two integers representing image width and height are returned as a tuple.
The _bytes_to_int32 function uses bitwise left shift and bitwise all, which is the vertical bar or the
pipe symbol together with indexing of the bytes object to reassemble the integer.
Notice that indexing into a bytes object returns an integer.
Let's try our new BMP dimensions function on the mandel.bmp file.