There's a notion in Python of file-like objects. This isn't as formal as a specific protocol like sequence
protocol is for tuple objects, but thanks to the polymorphism afforded by duck typing it works well in practice.
This is where the easier to ask forgiveness than permission philosophy comes into its own.
If you want to perform seek on a file-like object without knowing in advance that it supports random access,
go ahead and try literally, but be prepared to fail if the seek method doesn't exit or does exist, but doesn't
behave as you expect. You might say
if it looks like a file and reads like a file, then it is a file.
We've actually seen this already. The objects returned to us when we opened files in text and binary mode
are actually of different types, although both with definitely file-like behavior.
We saw one of them in action back at the beginning of the course used to retrieve data from a URL on the internet.
Let's exploit this polymorphism across file-like objects by writing a function to count to the number
of words per line in a file and return that information as a list.
Now we'll open a regular text file containing the fragment of T.S. Eliot's masterpiece we created earlier
and pass it to our new function. The actual type of real_file is _io.TextIOWrapper, which is an internal
Python implementation detail. We'll now do the same using a file-like object representing a web resource
referred to by a URL. (Typing) In this example, the type of web file is http.client.HTTPReponse, a quite
different thing. However, since they are both file-like objects, our function can work with both.
There's nothing magical about file-like objects. It's just a convenient and fairly informal description
for a set of expectations we can place on an object, which are exploited through duck typing.