Let's start by writing some text to a file. We'll be explicit about using the UTF-8 encoding because we
have no way of knowing what your default encoding is. We'll use keyword arguments to make things clearer still.
The first argument is the filename wasteland.txt. The mode argument is a string containing letters with
different meanings. In this case, W means write, and T means text.
All mode strings should consist of a read, write, or append mode.
One of R, W, or A with the optional plus modifier should be combined with a selective text or binary mode
T or B. So, typical mode strings might be 'wb', write binary, or 'at', append text.
Although both parts of the mode code support defaults, we recommend being explicit for the sake of readability.
The exact type of the object returned by open depends on how the file was opened, dynamic typing in action.
But for our purposes it's sufficient to know that the object returned is a file-like object, and as such
we can expect it to support certain attributes and methods. We've shown previously how we can request
help from modules and methods and types, but in fact we can request help on instances too.
This makes sense when you remember that everything is an object.
Browsing through the help we can see that F supports a method write.
Quit the help with Q, and continue at the REPL. The write call returns the number of codepoints or characters
written to the file. Let's write a few more lines. It is the caller's responsibility to provide newline
characters where they are needed. There is no writeline method. (Typing)
When we finish writing, we should remember to close the file by calling the close method, f.close().
Note that when we close the file all the contents become visible.
Closing files is important. If you now exit the REPL and look in your file system on Unix with ls - l, you should
see the wasteland.txt file with 78 bytes. On Windows with dir, you should see wasteland.txt with 79 bytes.
This is because Python's universal newline behavior for files has translated the line endings to your
system's native endings.
The difference is because Python's universal newline behavior for files has translated the line endings
to your platform's native endings.
The number returned by the write method is the number of codepoints or characters in the string passed
to write, not the number of bytes written to the file after encoding a universal newline translation.
In general, when working with text files, you cannot sum the quantities returned by write to determine
the length of the file in bytes.