To read the file back, we use open again, but pass a different mode string,
in this case 'rt' for read text. If we know how many bytes to read or if we want to read the whole file, we can
use the read function. Looking back through our REPL, we can see that the first write was 32 characters long.
We can read that back with a call to the read method. In text mode the read method accepts the number of characters
to read from the file, not the number of bytes. The call returns the text and advances the file pointer to
the end of what was read. The return type is str because we opened the file in text mode.
To read all the remaining data in the file, we can call read without an argument.
This gives us parts of two lines in one string. Note the newline character in the middle.
At the end of the file, further calls to read return an empty string.
Normally when we are finished reading a file we would close it, but for the purposes of this exercise we'll
keep the file open and move the file pointer back to the beginning of the file using the seek method with
a 0 offset from the start of the file. The return value is the new file pointer position.
Using read for text is quite awkward, and thankfully Python provides us with better tools for reading
text files line-by-line. First of these is the readline() function.
The returned lines are terminated by a single newline character if there is one present in the file.
The last line here does not terminate with a newline because there is no newline sequence at the end of the file.
You shouldn't rely on the string returned by readline being terminated by a newline.
Again, the universal newline support will have translated to /n from whatever the platform native newline
sequence is. Once we reach the end of the file, further calls to readline return an empty string.
Let's rewind again with seek. Sometimes when we know we want to read every line in the file and we're sure
we have enough memory, we can read all lines into a list with the readlines() method.
This is particularly useful if pausing the file involves hopping backwards and forwards between lines.
It's much easier to do this with a list than with a file stream of characters.
This time we'll close the file before moving on with g.close().