The culmination of these increasingly sophisticated text file reading tools is the fact that file objects
support the iterator protocol with each iteration yielding the next line in the file.
This means they can be used in for loops and any other place where an iterator can be used.
At this point, we'll take the opportunity to create a Python module, files.py.
We'll use this to contain the code for the following example. When run, this program opens the filename
passes its command line argument, and iterates over the file with a for loop line-by-line printing each
line as it goes. Let's run this program directly from the system
command line passing the name of our text file wasteland.txt. The double line spacing occurs because
each line of the poem is terminated by a newline, and then print adds its own.
To fix that we could use the strip method to remove the whitespace from the end of each line prior to printing.
Instead, we'll use the write method of the standard out stream.
This is exactly the same write method used to write to the file.
Files and streams are closely related and can be used because the stream is a file-like object.
We can get hold of a reference to the standard out stream from the sys module.
Rerunning, we now get single-space text. Now alas it's time to move on from one of the most important poems
of the 20th century and get to grips with context managers.