For the next demonstration, we're going to need a data file containing some numbers.
We'll write a sequence of numbers called Recaman sequence to a text file with one number per line.
Recaman sequence itself isn't important to this exercise. We just need a way of generating numeric data,
so we won't be explaining the sequence generator. Feel free to experiment though.
The module contains a generator for yielding the Recaman numbers and a function which writes the start
of the sequence to a file using the writelines method. A generator expression is used to convert each number
to a string and add a newline. Itertool's islice is used to truncate the otherwise infinite sequence.
We'll write the first 1000 Recaman numbers to a file by executing the module passing the filename and series
length as command line arguments.
Now let's make a complimentary module, series.py, which reads this data file back in.
This simply uses a for loop to iterate over the file reading one line at a time and strips the newline with
a call to the strip string method and coverts it to an integer.
Running it from the command line, everything works as expected.
Now let's deliberately create an exceptional situation.
Open Recaman.dat in a text editor and replace one of the numbers with something that isn't a stringified integer.
Save the data file, and rerun series.py. The int constructor raises a ValueError, which is unhandled,
so the program terminates with a stack trace. One problem here is that our f.close() call was never executed.
To fix that, we can insert a try/finally block. Now the file will always be closed.
Doing so opens up the opportunity for another refactoring. We can replace the for loop with a list comprehension
and return the list directly. Even in this situation close will be called.
The finally block is called; however, the try block is exited.