Up to now, our examples have all followed a pattern. Open a file, work with the file, and close the file.
The close is important, because it informs the underlying operating system that you're done working
with a file. If you don't close a file when you're done with it, it's possible to lose data.
There may be pending rights buffered up, which might not get written completely.
Furthermore, if you're opening lots of files, your system may run out of resources.
Since we always want to pair every open with a close, we want a mechanism that enforces that and makes sure
it happens even if we forget.
This need for resource cleanup is common enough that Python implements a specific control flow structure
called with-block to support it. With-blocks can be used with any object which supports the context-manager
protocol, and that includes the file objects returned by open().
Exploiting the context-manager nature of the file object and using a with-block, our read_series function
can become very simple. We no longer need to call close explicitly because the with construct will call
it for us when and by whatever means execution exits the block.
Now we can go back and modify our Recaman series writing program to use a with-block too.
This also removes the need for an explicit close.