To demonstrate handling of binary files, we need an interesting binary data format.
The BMP file format contains device-independent bitmaps and is simple enough that we can make a BMP file
writer from scratch in this session.
The code will be placed in a module bmp.py and is straightforward from a file handling point of view.
For simplicity sake, we have decided to deal with 8-bit grayscale images, which have the nice property
that they are 1 byte per pixel. The write_grayscale function accepts two arguments, the filename and
a collection of pixels. As the docstring points out, this collection should be a sequence of iterable
series of integers. A list of lists of int objects will do just fine.
Each int is a pixel value from 0 to 255. Each inner list is a row of pixels from left to right, and the outer
list is a list of pixel rows from top to bottom. The first thing we do is figure out the size of the image by
counting the number of rows to give the height and number of items in the 0th row to get the width.
We assume, but don't check that all rows have the same length.
In production code, that's a check we would want to make. Next we open the file for write in binary mode using
the 'wb' mode string. We don't specify an encoding. That makes no sense for raw binary files.
Inside the with-block we start writing what is called the BMP Header, which begins the BMP format.
The header must start with a so-called magic byte sequence 'BM' to identify it as a BMP file.
We use the write method, and because the file was opened in binary mode, we must pass a bytes object.
The next four bytes should hold the 32-bit integer containing the file size, but we don't know that yet.
We could've computed it in advance, but we'll take a different approach of writing a placeholder value
for now, then returning to this point later to fill in the details.
To be able to come back to this point, we use the tell method of the file object to give us the offset from the
beginning of the file for the file pointer. We'll store this in a variable, which will act as a sort of bookmark.
We write four 0 bytes as a placeholder using escaping syntax to specify the zeros.
The next two pairs of bytes are unused in this format, so we'll just write 0 bytes for them too.
The next four bytes are for another 32-bit integer, which should contain the offsetting bytes from the
beginning of the file to the start of the pixel data. We don't know that value yet either, so we'll store
another bookmark using tell and write another 4-byte placeholder.
We'll return here shortly when we know more. The next section is called the Image Header.
The first thing we have to do is write the length of the image header as a 32-bit integer.
In our case, the header will always be 40 bytes long. We'll just hardwire that in hexadecimal.
Notice that the BMP format is little-endian, the least significant byte is written first.
The next 4 bytes are the image width as a little-endian 32-bit integer.
We call a module scope implementation detail function here called _int32_to_bytes, which converts
an int object into a bytes object containing exactly 4 bytes. We then use the same function again to deal
with the image height. The remainder of the header is essentially fixed for 8-bit grayscale images, and
the details aren't important here except to note that the whole header does in fact total 40 bytes.
Each pixel in an 8-bit BMP image is an index into a color table with 256 entries.
Each entry is a 4-byte blue, green, red color. For grayscale images, we need to write 256 four byte gray
values on a linear scale. This snippet is fertile ground for experimentation, and a natural enhancement
to this function would be to be able to supply this pallet separately as an argument to the function.
At last we are ready to write the pixel data. But before we do, we make a note of the current file pointer offset
using tell() as this is one of the locations we need to go back and fill in.
Writing the pixel data is straightforward enough. We use the reversed built-in function to flip the order
of the rows. BMP images are written from bottom to top. For each row, we simply pass the iterable series
of integers to bytes constructor. If any of the integers are out of the range 0-255, the constructor will
raise a ValueError. After the pixel data, we are at the end of the file.
We undertook to record this offset value earlier, so we record the precision using tell() into an end of
file bookmark variable. Now we can rewind and fulfill our promises by replacing the placeholder offsets
we recorded with the real thing. To do this, we seek back to the size_bookmark we remembered back near the
beginning of the file and write to the size stored in the eof_bookmark as a little-endian 32-bit integer
using our _int32_to_bytes function. Finally, we seek to the pixel data offset placeholder bookmarked
by pixel_offset_bookmark and write the 32-bit integer stored in pixel_data_bookmark.
As we exit the with-block, we can rest assured that the context manager will close the file and commit any
buffered writes to the file system.