Hello. My name is Austin Bingham. Welcome to the eighth module of the Python Fundamentals course.
Here we'll cover classes, Python's tools for creating new types.
You can get a long way in Python using the built-in scaler and collection types.
For many problems, the built-in types and those available in the Python Standard library are completely
sufficient. Sometimes though they aren't quite what's required, and the ability to create custom types
is where classes come in.
As we've seen, all objects in Python have a type, and when we report that type using the type built-in function,
the result is couched in terms of class.
Classes are a means of defining the structure and behavior of objects at the time we create the object.
Generally speaking, the type of an object is fixed throughout its lifetime.
As such, classes act as a sort of template or pattern according to which new objects are constructed.
The class of an object controls its initialization in which attributes and methods are available through
the object. For example, on a string object the methods we can use on that object such as split are defined
in the str class.
Classes are a key piece of machinery for object-oriented programming, and although it's often true that
OOP is useful for making complex problems more tractable, it also commonly has the effect of making the
solution to simple problems unnecessarily complex. A great thing about Python is that it's highly object
oriented without forcing you to deal with classes until you really need them.
This sets the language starkly apart from Java and C#.