Now we'll show how it's quite possible to write nice object-oriented code without needing classes.
We have a requirement to produce boarding cards for our passengers in alphabetical order; however, we
realize that the flight class is probably not a good home for details of printing boarding passes.
We could go ahead and create a boarding card printer class, but that's probably overkill.
Remember that functions are objects too and are perfectly sufficient for many cases.
Don't feel compelled to make classes and objects without good reason.
Rather than have a card printer query all the passenger details from the flight, we'll follow the object-
oriented design principle of tell, don't ask, and have the flight tell a simple card printing function
what to do. First, the card printer, which is just a module-level function.
The new Python feature here is the use of line continuation backslash characters, which allow us to split
a long statement over several lines. This is used together with implicit string concatenation of adjacent
strings to produce one long string with no line breaks. We then measure the length of this output line,
build some banners and borders around it, and then concatenate the lines together using the join method
called on newline operator before printing the whole card followed by a blank line.
Note that the card printer doesn't know anything about flights or aircraft.
It's very loosely coupled. You can probably easily envisage an HTML card printer that has the same interface.
To the flight class we add a new method, make_boarding_cards, which accepts the card_printer.
This tells the card_printer to print each passenger having sorted a list of passenger seat tuples obtained
from a _passenger_seats() implementation detail method. Note the leading underscore.
That method is in fact a generator function which searches all seats for occupants yielding the passenger
and the seat number as they are found. Now if we run this on the REPL we can see that the new boarding card print
system works.