Polymorphism is a programing language feature which allows us to use objects of different types through
a uniform interface. The concept of polymorphism applies to functions and more complex objects.
We've just seen an example of polymorphism with the card printing example.
The make_boarding_card method didn't need to know about an actual or as we say concrete card printing
type, only the abstract details of its interface, essentially just the order of its arguments.
Replacing our console card printer with the putative HTML card printer would exercise polymorphism.
Polymorphism in Python is achieved through duck typing. Duck typing is in turn named after the duck test
attributed to James William Riley the American poet. "When I see a bird that walks like a duck and swims
like a duck and quacks like a duck, I call that bird a duck."
Duck typing where an object's fitness for a particular use is only determined at runtime is the cornerstone
of Python's object system. This is in contrast to statically typed languages where a compiler determines
if an object can be used. And in particular, it means that an object's suitability is not based on inheritance
hierarchies, base classes, or anything except the attributes an object has at the time of use.
Let's return to our aircraft class. The design of this class is somewhat flawed in that objects instantiated
using it depend on being supplied with a seating configuration that matches the aircraft model, which
for the purposes of this exercise we assumed is fixed per model.
Better and simpler perhaps to get rid of the Aircraft class entirely and make separate classes for each
specific model of aircraft with a fixed seating configuration.
Here is an AirbusA319, and here's a Boeing777. These two aircraft classes have no explicit relationship
to each other or to our original aircraft class beyond having identical interfaces to each other with
the exception of the initializer, which now takes fewer arguments.
As such, we can use these new types in place of each other. Let's change our make_flight() method into
make_flights() to use them. The different types of aircraft work fine when used with flight because they
both quack like ducks or fly like planes or something. Duck typing and polymorphism is very important
in Python. In fact, it's the basis for the collection protocols we discussed such as iterator, iterable,
and sequence.