Inheritance is a mechanism whereby one class can be derived from a base-class allowing us to make behavior
more specific in the sub-class. In nominally typed languages such as Java, class-based inheritance
is the means by which runtime polymorphism is achieved. Not so in Python as we have just demonstrated.
The fact that no Python method calls or attribute lookups are bound to actual objects until the point at
which they are called known as late binding means we can attempt polymorphism with any object, and we'll
succeed if the object fits. Although inheritance in Python can be used to facilitate polymorphism, after
all derived classes will have the same interfaces as the base classes, inheritance in Python is most useful
for sharing implementation between classes. As usual, this will make much more sense with an example.
We would like our aircraft class's AirbusA319 and Boeing777 to provide a way of returning the total number
of seats. We'll add a method called num_seats to both classes to do this.
Unfortunately, we now have duplicate code across two classes, and as we add more aircraft types, the code
duplication will worsen. The solution we look at here is to extract the common elements of AirbusA319
and Boeing777 into a base class from which both aircraft types will derive.
Let's recreate the class Aircraft, this time with the goal of using it as a base class.
It contains just the method we want to inherit into the derived classes.
This class isn't usable on its own because it depends on a method called seating_plan, which isn't available
at this level. Any attempt to use it standalone will fail. The class is abstract in so far as it is never useful
to instantiate it alone. Now the derived classes. We specify inheritance in Python using parentheses
containing the base class name immediately after the class name in the class statement.
Here's the Airbus class, and this is the Boeing class. Let's exercise them at the REPL.
We can see that both subtype aircraft inherited the num_seats() method, which now works as expected because
the call to seating_plan is successfully resolved on the self object at runtime.
Now that we have the base Aircraft class, we can hoist other common functionality into it.
In this case, initializer and registration methods are identical between the two subtypes.
Now the derived classes only contain the specifics for that aircraft type.
All shared functionality is inherited from the base class.
Thanks to duck typing, inheritance is less used in Python than in other languages.
This is generally seen as a good thing because inheritance is a very tight coupling between classes.