Let's make our class a little more interesting by adding a so-called instance method, which returns the
flight number.
Methods are just functions defined within the class, and instance methods are functions which can be
called on objects or instances of our class such as F. Instance methods must accept a reference to the instance
on which the method was called as the first argument, and by convention this argument is always called self.
We have no way of configuring the flight number value yet, so we'll just return a constant string.
Now from a fresh REPL let's import that and see how it works.
Notice that when we call the method we do not provide the instance F for the actual argument itself in the
argument list. That's because the standard method invocation form with the dot is simply syntactic sugar
for the class name followed by a dot followed by the method name with the instance passed as the first argument.
If you try the latter, you'll find that it works as expected, although you'll almost never see this form
used for real.