Now we can proceed with implementing a simple booking system.
For each flight we simply need to keep track of who is sitting in each seat.
We'll represent the seat allocations using a list of dictionaries.
The list will contain one entry for each seat row, and each entry will be a dictionary from seat letter to
occupant name. If the seat is unoccupied, it will contain None.
We initialize the seating plan in the flight initializer using this fragment.
In the first line we retrieve the seating plan for the aircraft and use tuple unpacking to put the row and
seat identifiers into local variables. In the second line we create a list for the seat allocations.
Rather than continually deal with the fact that row indices are one-based whereas Python lists are zero-
based, we choose to waste one entry at the beginning of the list.
This first wasted entry is the single element list containing None.
To this single element list we concatenate another list containing one entry for each real row in the aircraft.
This list is constructed by a list comprehension which iterates over the rows object, which is the range
of row numbers retrieved from the aircraft in the previous line.
We're not actually interested in the row number since we know it will match up with the list index in the
final index, so we discard it by using the dummy underscore variable.
The item expression part of the list comprehension is itself a comprehension, specifically a dictionary
comprehension. This iterates over each letter for the row and creates a mapping from the single character
string to None to indicate an empty seat. We use a list comprehension rather than list replication with
the multiplication operator because we want a distinct dictionary object to be created for each row.
Here's the code after we put it into the initializer. Before we go further, let's test our code in the REPL.
Thanks to the fact that everything is public, we can access implementation details during development,
and it's clear enough that we're doing so since the leading underscores remind us what's public and what's not.
That's accurate, but not particularly beautiful. Let's try again with pretty print.
Perfect. Now we'll add behavior to flight to allocate seats to passengers.
To keep this simple, a passenger will simply be a string name.
Most of this code is validation of the seat designator and contains some interesting snippets.
Methods are functions so deserve docstrings too. We get the seat letter by using negative indexing into
the seat string. We test that the seat letter is valid by checking for membership of seat letters using
the in membership testing operator. We extract the row number using string slicing to take all but the
last character. We try to convert the row number substring to an integer using the int constructor.
If this fails, we catch the ValueError and in the handler raise a new ValueError with a more appropriate
message payload. We conveniently validate the row number by using the in operator against the rows object,
which is a range. We can do this because range objects support the container protocol.
We check that the requested seat is unoccupied using an identity test with None.
If it's occupied, we raise a ValueError. If we get this far, everything is in good shape, and we can assign
the seat. It also contains a bug, but we'll discover that soon enough.
Let's try our seat allocator at the REPL. Doing so, we see that we get a TypeError in allocate_seat.
Early on in your object-oriented Python career you're likely to see TypeError messages like this quite often.
The problem has occurred because we forgot to include the self argument in the definition of the allocate_seat
method. Once we fix that, we can try again. If we create our flight object as normal, we then allocate_seat
12A, but if we try to allocate_seat 12A a second time we get a ValueError.
Now we allocate 15F and 15E, but if we try to allocate E27 we get a ValueError because E27 is obviously not
a seat. We now allocate 1C and 1D, but if we try to seat Larry Wall in seat DD we get yet another ValueError
because of course DD is not a valid seat. After that we pretty print to see how things look.
The Dutchman is quite lonely there in row 12, so we'd like to move him back to row 15 with the Danes.
To do so, we'll need a relocate passenger method.