First we'll perform a small refactoring and extract the seat designator, parsing, and validation logic
into its own method parse_seat. We use a leading underscore here because this method is an implementation
detail. The new parse_seat method returns a tuple with an integer row number and a seat letter string.
This leave allocate_seat much simpler. See the call to parse_seat, and notice that method calls within
the same object also require explicit qualification with the self prefix.
Now we've laid the groundwork for our relocate_passenger method.
This parses and validates the from_seat and to_seat arguments and then moves the passenger to the new location.
It's also getting tiresome recreating the flight object each time, so we'll add a module level convenience
function for that too. It's quite normal to mix related functions and classes in the same module.
Now let's see that at the REPL. You may find it remarkable that we have access to the flight class when we
have only imported a function make_flight(). This is quite normal, and it's a powerful aspect of Python's
dynamic type system that allows us this very loose coupling between code.
Let's go on and move Guido back to 15 with his fellow Europeans.
It's important during booking to know how many seats are available.
To this end, we'll write a num_available_seats method. This is achieved using two nested generator
expressions. The outer expression filters for all rows, which are not None.
This excludes our dummy first row. The value of each item in the outer expression is the sum of the number
of None values in each row. This inner expression iterates over values of the dictionary and adds one for
each None found. See how we split the outer expression over three lines to improve readability. (Typing)
And just to check, let's do a little bit of math.