Welcome to the Python Fundamentals course by Robert Smallshire and Austin Bingham.
My name is Robert Smallshire, and I'll be presenting this Getting Started module of the Python Fundamentals
course.
In this module we'll cover obtaining and installing Python on your system for Windows, Ubuntu Linux,
and Mac OS X. We'll write some basic Python code and become acquainted with the essentials of Python programming
culture such as The Zen of Python, although never forgetting the origins of the name of the language.
There are two major versions of the Python language, Python 2, which is the widely deployed legacy language,
and Python 3, which is the present and future of the language.
Most Python code will work without modification between the last version of Python 2, which is Python
2.7, and recent versions of Python 3 such as Python 3.3. However, there are some key differences, and in
a strict sense the languages are incompatible. We'll be using Python 3.3 for this course, but we'll point
out key differences with Python 2 as we go. It's also very likely that this being a fundamentals course
everything we present will apply to future versions of Python 3, so don't be afraid to try those as they
become available.
Before we can start programming in Python, we need to get ahold of a Python environment.
Python is a highly portable language available on all major operating systems.
You'll be able to complete this course on Windows, Mac, or Linux, and the only major section where we diverge
into platform specifics is coming right up as we install Python 3.
As we cover the three platforms, feel free to skip over the sections which aren't relevant for you.