Now we've examined some basic built-in types. We'll look at two important control flow structures, which
depend on conversions to the bool type, while loops, but first if statements.
Conditional statements allow us to branch execution based on the value of an expression.
The form of the statement is the if keyword followed by an expression terminated by a colon to introduce
a new block. The expression is converted to bool as if by the bool constructor.
Let's try this at the REPL.
Remembering to indent four spaces within the block, we add some code to be executed if the condition is
True followed by a blank line to terminate the block at which point the block will execute because self-
evidently the condition is true. Conversely, if the condition is False, the code in the block does not execute.
Because the expression used with the if statement will be converted to bool just as if the bool constructor
had been used, this form (Typing) is exactly equivalent to this form. (Typing)
Thanks to this useful shorthand, explicit conversion to bool using the bool constructor is rarely used
in Python. The if statement supports an optional else clause, which goes in a block introduced by the else
keyword followed by a colon, which is indented to the same level as the if keyword.
To start the else block in this case, we just omit the indentation after the three dots. (Typing)
For multiple conditions, you might be tempted to do something like this, nesting if statements.
Whenever you find yourself with an else block containing a nested if statement like this, you should consider
instead using Python's elif keyword, which is a combined else/if.
As The Zen of Python reminds us, flat is better than nested. This version is altogether easier to read.
We'll quickly demonstrate it at the REPL. (Typing)