We've covered a lot of ground in this Getting Started module. Let's summarize what we've seen.
We started by obtaining and installing Python 3 for Windows, Ubuntu Linux, and Mac OS X.
We then looked at the Read-Eval-Print-Loop or REPL, and how it allows us to interactively explore Python code.
We learned some simple arithmetic operators with plus, minus, multiply, divide, modulus, and the integer
division operator with double slash. We discovered we could give objects names with the assignment operator
using the equals symbol. We learned how to print objects, and we showed you how to exit the REPL, which is
different on Windows with Control+Z or Linux and Mac with Control+D.
We showed how Python uses significant indentation of code to demarcate code blocks.
Each indent level is usually four spaces. And we told you about Python Enhancement Proposals, the documents
which govern the evolution of the Python language. In particular, we briefly looked at PEP 8, which is
the Python Style Guide, which we follow in this course, and PEP 20, The Zen of Python, which gives useful
advice on writing Pythonic code.
We looked at importing Python's Standard Library modules using the import statement.
Import has three forms: Import module, from module import function, and from module import function
as alias. We used all three of these forms during this course module.
We showed how to find and browse help(), particularly useful for discovering the Standard Library.
We looked at the four built-in scalar types int, float, None, and bool and showed how to convert between
these types and use their literal forms. We looked at the six relational operators equality, inequality,
less-than, greater-than, less-than or equal to, and greater-than or equal to.
These are used for equivalence testing and ordering. We demonstrated structuring conditional code
with if, elif, else structures. We shared iterating with while loops and how to interrupt execution of
infinite loops using Control+C, which generates a keyboard interrupt exception.
We gave an example of how to break out of a loop using the break statement, which breaks out of the innermost
loop onto the first statement immediately following the loop, and along the way we looked at the augmented
assignment operators for modifying objects in place such as counter variables.
We also looked at requesting text from the user at the console with the built-in input() function.
Next time here on Python Fundamentals we'll continue our exploration of Python's built-in types and
control flow structures by looking at strings, lists, dictionaries, and for-loops.
We'll even be using Python to fetch some data from the web for processing.
Thanks for watching, and we'll see you in the next module.