Start your Python 3 interpreter using the Python or Python 3 command for Windows or Unix-like systems
respectively. The control flow structures of Python such as for loops, while loops, and if statements
are all introduced by statements which are terminated by a colon indicating that the body of the construct
is to follow. For example, for loops require a body. So, if you enter for i in range(5), Python will change
the prompt to three dots to request you provide the body. One distinctive and sometimes controversial
aspect of Python is that leading whitespace is syntactically significant.
What this means is that Python uses indentation levels rather than the braces used by other languages
to demarcate code blocks. By convention, contemporary Python code is indented by four spaces for each
level, so we provide those four spaces and a statement to form the body of our loop, x = i * 10.
Our loop body will contain a second statement. So, after pressing Return, at the next three dot prompt
we enter another four spaces followed by a call to the built-in print function.
To terminate our block, we must enter a blank line into the REPL.
With the block complete, Python executes the pending code printing out the multiples of 10 less than 50.
Looking at a screen full of Python code, we can see how the indentation clearly matches, and in fact must
match the structure of the program. Even if we replace the code by gray lines, the structure of the program
is clear. Each statement terminates by a colon, starts a new line, and introduces an additional level
of indentation, which continues until a dedent restores the indentation to a previous level.
Each level of indent is typically four spaces, although we'll cover the rules in more detail in a moment.
Python's approach to significant whitespace has three great advantages.
First, it forces developers to use a single level of indentation in a code block.
This is generally considered good practice in any language because it makes code much more readable.
Second, code with a significant whitespace doesn't need to be cluttered with unnecessary braces, and
you never need to have a code standard debate about where the braces should go.
All code blocks in Python code are easily identifiable, and everyone writes them the same way.
Third, significant whitespace requires that a consistent interpretation must be given to the structure
of the code by the author, the Python runtime system, and future maintainers who need to read the code,
so you can never have code that contains a block from Python's point of view, but which doesn't look like
it from a cursory human perspective.
The rules for Python indentation can seem complex, but are straightforward in practice.
The whitespace you use can either be spaces or tabs. The general consensus is that spaces are preferable
to tabs, and four spaces has become standard in the Python community.
One essential rule is never to mix spaces and tabs. The Python interpreter will complain, and your colleagues
will hunt you down. You are allowed to use different amounts of indentation at different times if you wish.
The essential rule is that consecutive lines of code at the same indentation level are considered to be
part of the same code block. There are some exceptions to these rules, but they almost always have to do
with improving code readability in other ways, for example, by breaking up necessarily long statements
over multiple lines.
This vigorous approach to code formatting is programming as Guido indented it.
The philosophy of placing a high value on code quality such as readability gets to the very heart of Python
culture, something we'll take a short look at now.