Python comes with a number of built-in data types. These include primitive scalar types like integers,
as well as collection types like dictionaries. These built-in types are powerful enough to be used alone
for many programming needs, and they can be used as building blocks for creating more complex data types.
In this section we'll cover the basic scalar built-in types int, float, None, and bool.
We'll provide basic information about these now showing their literal forms and how to create them.
We've already seen quite a lot of Python integers in action. Python integers are signed and have for all
practical purposes unlimited precision.
Integer literals in Python are specified in decimal, but may also be specified in binary with a 0b prefix,
up top with a 0o prefix, or hexadecimal with a 0x prefix. We can also construct integers by a call to the int
constructor, which can convert from other numeric types such as floats to integers.
Note that rounding is always towards 0. We can also convert strings to integers.
To convert from base 3, use int and then 10000 as a string comma 3.
Floating point numbers are supported in Python by the float type.
Python floats are implemented as IEEE-754 double precision floating point numbers with 53 bits of binary
precision. This is equivalent to between 15 and 16 significant digits in decimal.
Any literal number containing a decimal point or a letter E is interpreted by Python as a float.
Scientific notation can be used. So, for large numbers such as the approximate speed of light in meters
per second 3 times 10 to the 8, we can write 3e8. And for small numbers like Planck's constant 1.616 times
10 to the -35, we can enter 1.616e-35. Notice how Python automatically switches the display representation
to the most readable form. As for integers, we can convert to floats from other numeric or string types
using the float constructor from an int and from a string. This is also how we create the special floating-
point values nan or not a number and also positive and negative infinity.
The result of any calculation involving int and float is promoted to a float.
Python has a special null value called None with a capital N.
None is frequently used to represent the absence of a value.
The Python REPL never prints None results, so typing None into the REPL has no effect.
None can be bound to a variable name just like any other object, and we can test whether an object is None
by using Python's is operator. We can see here that the response is True, which brings us conveniently
onto the bool type.
The bool type represents logical states and plays an important role in several of Python's control flow
structures as we'll see shortly.
As you would expect, there are two bool values, True and False, both with initial capitals, and also a bool
constructor, which can be used to convert from other types to bool.
Let's look at how it works. For integers, 0 is considered falsey, and all other values truthy. (Typing)
We see the same behavior with floats where only 0 is considered falsey. (Typing)
When converting from collections such as strings or lists, only empty collections are treated as falsey.
Converting from lists, which we'll look at shortly, (Typing) and strings (Typing) in particular, you
cannot use the bool constructor to covert from the string representations of True and False because the
string False is not empty. These conversions to bool are important because they are widely used in Python
if statements and while loops, which accept bool values into the condition.