Let's review what we've covered in this module. Python code is placed in .py files called modules.
Modules can be executed directly by passing them as the first argument to the Python interpreter.
Modules can also be imported into the REPL, at which point all top-level statements in the module are
executed in order. Named functions are defined using the def keyword followed by the function name and the
argument list in parentheses. We can return objects from functions using the return statement, and return
statements without a parameter return None, as does the implicit return at the end of every function body.
We can detect whether a module has been imported or executed by examining the value of the special double
underscore name variable. If it is equal to the string double underscore main, our module has been executed
directly as a program. By executing a function if this condition is met using the top-level
if __name__ == __main__ idiom at the end of our module, we can make our module both usefully importable and
executable, an important technique even for short scripts. Module code is only executed once on first import.
The def keyword is a statement, which binds executable code to a function name.
Command line arguments can be accessed as a list of strings accessible through the argv attribute of the sys module.
The 0th command line argument is the script filename, so the item at index 1 is the first true argument.
Literal strings is the first line of a function definition from the function's docstring.
They are typically triple quoted multiline strings containing usage information.
Function documentation provided in docstrings can be retrieved using the Help function in the REPL.
Module docstrings should be placed near the beginning of the module prior to any Python statements,
such as import statements. Comments in Python commence with the hash character and continue to the end of
the line. The first line of the module can contain a special comment called a shebang allowing the
program loader to launch the correct Python interpreter on all major platforms.
Next time here on Python Fundamentals, we'll dig into Python's object model, looking at how values are passed
to and returned from functions. We investigate the nature of dynamic typing in Python and focus on the rules
of variable scope. Thanks for watching, and we'll see you in the next module.