Let's organize our words module using functions. We'll move all the code, except the import statement,
into a function called fetch_words. You do that simply by adding the def statement and indenting the code
below it by one extra level. Save the module and reload
the module using a fresh Python REPL. The module imports, but the words are not fetched until we call the
fetch_words function. Alternatively, we can import our specific function.
So far, so good. But what happens when we try to run our module directly from the operating system shell?
Exit the REPL with Control +D on Mac or Linux or Control +Z on Windows, and run python3 passing the module
filename words.py. No words are printed. This is because all executing the module does now is define a
function and then immediately exit. To make a module from which we can usefully import functions into the
REPL, and which can be run as a script, we need to learn a new Python idiom.
The Python runtime system defines some special variables and attributes, the names of which are delimited by
double underscores. One such variable is called __name__ and gives us the means for our module to detect
whether it has been run as a script or imported into another module or the REPL.
To see how, add print__name__ at the end of your module, outside the fetch_words function.
First of all, let's import the modified words module back into the REPL with import words.
We can see that when imported, double underscore name does indeed evaluate to the module's name.
As a brief aside, if we import the module again, the print statement will not be executed.
Module code is only executed once on first import. Now, let's try running the module as a script with
python3 words.py. Now the special name variable is equal to the string __main__, which is also delimited
by double underscores. Our module can use this behavior to detect how it is being used.
We replaced the print statement with an if statement, which tests the value of double underscore
name (__name__), and if it is equal to double underscore main (__main__), executes our function.
Now we can safely import our module without unduly executing our function.
And we can usefully run our function as a script.