Hi. My name is Robert Smallshire. Welcome to the fifth module of the Python Fundamentals course where
we look in more depth at the built-in collection types of the Python language and explore the various protocols
that unite them.
In this module we'll revisit some collection types we've already explored:
Str or string, the immutable sequence of Unicode codepoints; list, the mutable sequence of objects;
and dict, the mutable mapping from immutable keys to mutable objects.
We'll also cover some new ones: Tuple, the immutable sequence of objects; range for arithmetic progressions
of integers; and set, a mutable collection of unique immutable objects.
We won't cover the bytes type further here. We've already discussed its essential differences with str,
and most of what we learned about str can also be applied to bytes.
This is not an exhaustive list of Python collection types, but it's completely sufficient for the overwhelming
majority of Python 3 programs you'll encounter in the wild or are likely to write yourself.
In this module we'll be covering these collections in this order, and then round off with an overview of
the protocols that unite these collections, which allow them to be used in consistent and predictable ways.
First up is tuple.