To demonstrate this, we'll used nested lists with the inner list serving as mutable objects.
Here's a list containing two elements, each of which is itself a list.
Let's look at what's going on under the covers as Python constructs this data structure.
First, two integer objects are created containing the values 1 and 2 respectively.
The elements of the first inner list are references to these two integer objects.
Now two more integer objects are created containing the values 3 and 4 respectively.
The elements of the second inner list are references to these integer objects.
Now the outer list is created, its elements containing references to the two inner lists.
Finally, the reference named A is bound to the outer list. What happens when we copy the list?
Here we use the full slice technique, but any of the three techniques we've shown will have the same effect.
We're requesting a copy of outer list, so it's elements, which contain references to the two inner lists,
are duplicated. These references refer to the same inner lists as the original list A.
Once the list copy is complete, we bind a new reference named B to the new list.
We can confirm that the lists are distinct objects by testing with A is B, which returns False.
They do, however, contain equivalent values, which we can test with A == B, which returns True.
Not only are the elements at a(0) and b(0) equivalent, they actually refer to the same inner list object.
Now let's replace the element at a(0) with a new list containing 8 and 9.
This results in the construction of two new integer objects containing 8 and 9 respectively and the new
list, the elements of which are references to these two new integer objects.
The reference in a(0) is redirected to point to this new inner list object, and we can confirm that a(0)
now indeed points to the new list while b(0) is unmodified. What happens if we now append to the inner list
referred to by a(1)? Let's append a new integer object containing the value 5.
The new integer object is created and is referred to by an additional element in the inner list referred
to by a(1), so a(1) now refers to a list containing integers 3, 4, 5.
Significantly, because a(1) and b(1) refer to the same inner list, the list accessible through b(1) has
also been modified. Following these manipulations, the data structure referred to by A is a list containing
two elements, each of which itself is a list. The first inner list contains 8 and 9, and the second inner
list contains 3, 4, and 5. The data structure referred to by B is also a list containing two inner lists.
The first element refers to a list containing 1 and 2, and the second element also refers to the 3, 4, 5 list.