As for strings and tuples, lists support repetition using the multiplication operator.
It's simple enough to use. Here we repeat a list containing the integers 21 and 37 four times.
This form is rarely spotted in the wild. It's most often used for initializing a list of size known in advance
to a constant value such as 0. Here we create a list initialized with nine 0 elements.
Be aware though that in the case of mutable elements the same trap for the unwary that occurred with list
copying lurks here since repetition will repeat the reference without copying the value.
Let's demonstrate using nested lists as our mutable elements again.
We'll repeat a list five times. The mutable element it contains will be another list containing elements,
two -1 and +1. Let's see what Python needs to do to construct this data structure.
First, two integer objects are created containing the values -1 and +1 respectively.
These are referred to by the two elements of the inner list. Python then creates the outer list and the ranges
for its single element to contain a reference to the inner list.
Now the repetition operation is applied. A new list is created containing five elements, each of which
contains a copy of the single element in the original outer list.
All of these elements contain references to the same inner list object.
Now the temporary single element outer list can be disposed of.
Finally, this whole data structure is bound to a new named reference, S.
As expected, S contains five elements, each of which is the -1, +1 in a list.
Now let's append the integer 7 to the fourth inner list at index 3 in the outer list.
This creates a new integer object and a new element on the inner list containing a reference to that integer
object. We can see that all of the elements of the outer list have been modified because they do in fact all
refer to the same inner list.