To find an element in a list, use the index method passing the object you're searching for.
The elements are compared for equivalence or value equality until the one you're looking for is found
and its index returned. Here we create a list W containing the words the quick brown fox jumps over the lazy
dog using the string split method. Searching for fox using the index method returns the integer 3, which
of course allows us to get ahold of that element. If you search for a value that isn't present like unicorn,
you will receive a ValueError, which we'll learn how to handle gracefully in the next module.
Another means of searching is to count matching elements using the count method.
Here we count occurrences of the word the. If you just want to test for membership, you can use the in operator
or for nonmembership using the not in operator.
Elements are removed from lists using a keyword with which we have not yet become acquainted, del.
The del keyword takes a single parameter, which is a reference to a list element and removes it from the
list shortening the list in the process. Here we make a string U containing the words jackdaws love my big
sphinx of quartz using the string split method. We can delete the fourth element using del u(3) leaving
jackdaws love my sphinx of quartz. It's also possible to remove elements by value rather than by position
using the remove method. Here we pass jackdaws to that method giving us love my sphinx of quartz.
This is of course equivalent to using the del statement and the index method in combination.
Attempting to remove an item which is not present such as pyramid results in a ValueError.
Items can be inserted into lists using the insert method, which accepts the index of the new item and the
new item itself. Here we create a list A containing the words I accidently the whole universe.
We insert the word destroyed at index 2 using a call to the insert method giving us I accidentally destroyed
the whole universe. We can covert this list of words back into a string by calling the string join operator
on a space separator.